<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Castigio temporum, or, A Short view and reprehension of the errours and enormities of the times, both in church and state and what is the most probable means to cure the distempers in either.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31222</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1231A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28548</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10629490</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10629490</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45450</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31222)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45450)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1400:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Castigio temporum, or, A Short view and reprehension of the errours and enormities of the times, both in church and state and what is the most probable means to cure the distempers in either.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1], 25 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard Law School Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45450:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45450:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Caſtigatio Temporum:</hi> OR, A ſhort View and Reprehenſion Of the ERROURS and ENORMITIES Of the TIMES, BOTH In Church and State; And what is the moſt probable Means to cure the Diſtempers in either.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London,</hi> in the Year 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:45450:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>REader, It is more then time, (for <hi>Principlis obſtes, ſero Medicina pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur.</hi>)</p>
            <p>That thou and I ſhould at laſt look to our Duties; whenas Mankind, eſpecially in theſe Northern Regions, are become ſo faithleſs, and make ſuch haſte into forbidden wickedneſs, that not only in Faith and Religion, nothing is eſteemed which is not New, but in Morality alſo, thoſe Noblest Vertues of Juſtice and Obedience, are perſecuted as Vices; and their Contraries have the Reward which is due to Vertue ſet upon them.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45450:2"/>
            <head>A ſhort View and Caſtigation of the Publique Vices of the Times.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Oubtleſs it is a miſerable Slavery, where the Law is wandering or uncertain: <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſera ſervitus ubi Jus eſt vagum aut incogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi> If then it be a miſerable ſlavery where the Law is wandring and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, it muſt be there a more miſerable ſlavery where the Supreme Power (from whence all Law is derived) is wandering and uncertain: for there what can men truſt to? What ſecurity can any man have in his Life or Eſtate, when it is not known where he ſhall expect it? What <hi>Meum</hi> or <hi>Tuum</hi> can there be, where no man can tell from whence to derive it? And if it be true (as it is) That Juſtice comprehends in it ſelf all Vertues, <hi>(Juſtitia in ſeſe Virtutes continet omnes)</hi> what man can there be juſt, vertuous or honeſt, where he knows not to what to conform his Actions?</p>
            <p>In the beginning of our Diſtractions, whenas Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and Priviledge were oppoſed to Prerogative, they who aſſerted Liberty and Priviledge though then underſtood and called by one name, <hi>viz.</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet were compounded of two different Bodies, that is, two Houſes, one of Lords, another of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons: thoſe called themſelves the Kings hereditary Council; theſe, the Repreſentative Body of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. And theſe two, ſtrengthned by their Liberty and Priviledge, and aided by their Brethren the Scots, drive poor Prerogative out of all, to the utter extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of it.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:45450:3"/>
            <p>But becauſe all power is incompatible, and this power in two, and therefore not poſſible long to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt; the Repreſentative Body<note n="(a)" place="margin">6 <hi>Febr.</hi> 1648.</note> turns the Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Council out of doors, and ſeizes and rifles all Records and Papers in a moment, which they had been above eight years a doing. And then they ſay the Supreme Power of the Nation is reduced to the prime and original Fountain, <hi>viz.</hi> the People, and by the People to them. So that a ſmall part of the Houſe of Commons (for above one half were dead, or turned out of doors for adhering to the King; and the Army turn'd out at one time eleven of them that were left, and above one<note n="(b)" place="margin">6 <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1647.</note> half were impriſoned by the leſſer part, and the Army) which intire and whole, was not ſo much as a Court of Judicature, but to ſome things amongſt themſelves, nor had power to take any mans examination) aſcribe to themſelves the Supreme power of the Nation, and play ſuch reaks, as they became intolerable, even to their own creatures, who do by them, as they had done by the poor Prerogative creatures, the Lords<note n="(c)" place="margin">20 <hi>April</hi> 1653.</note>.</p>
            <p>And then comes, <hi>I</hi> Oliver, <hi>Captain General of all the Porces of the Commonwealth of</hi> England, Scotland, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>by the advice of my Officers of the Army,</hi> &amp;c. And he himſelf Taxes, and makes Laws. But this Scoene is ſoon altered: for the General, as he is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſummons<note n="(d)" place="margin">4 <hi>July</hi> 1653.</note> divers men from ſeveral parts to <hi>White-hall,</hi> and, if you believe <hi>Politicus,</hi> leaning upon a bay window, devolves to them the Sureme power of the Nation. Theſe are called Parliament too, give the General <hi>White-hall;</hi> but no damage to any of them: not any of them parted with any thing by this Gift. They make a Law, too, for Marriage by a Juſtice of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45450:3"/>Peace; and to hang men by a Law <hi>a Poſteriori,</hi> that is, a Law made after the Fact is committed, as you ſee in their Law for hanging the Saylors: It is not hard to finde this Act of Parliament; for theſe did not (I think) make many more beſides theſe three. They ſay, this pitiful thing could not agree in it ſelf, nor bear the burthen of the Nation upon their ſhoulders: and therefore<note n="(e)" place="margin">12 <hi>Decem.</hi> 1653.</note> they return the General all his power again; and ſo the General is as he was, and they may go home again, and look to their Cattle.</p>
            <p>And then <hi>December</hi> 16. 1653. the General is ſworn Lord Protector, and ſwears to an Inſtrument of God knows whoſe making, by which the Supreme power of this Nation, is in one perſon, and the free-born people of the Nation. <hi>Sept.</hi> 3. 1654. the Protector ſummons another Parliament (as he calls it) but with no better ſucceſs then the former. All this while Taxes are impoſed, diſtrained for, and levied without conſent of Parliament: Why what is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the Rights and Priviledges of the Engliſh Nation? Sure there is no ſuch thing as <hi>Magna Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> or the Statute <hi>De Tallagio non concedendo.</hi> But after that, the Protector got another company of men,<note place="margin" type="runSum">1657.</note> who called themſelves Parliament; theſe made or renewed him Protector, and gave him power to name his Succeſſor; and if you would have believed <hi>(ita vertere ſeria ludo)</hi> at next ſitting we ſhould have had the Other Houſe, and every ſecluded Member (that ſhould ſwear as he ought) ſhould have power to ſit in this Houſe: And yet was the condition of this poor Nation as perplexed as ever before. The Parliament hath given power to the Protector to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45450:4"/>his Succeſſor, and the Inſtrument hath given it to the Council; and who ſhall judge between theſe two? What is the power of the Inſtrument? What the power of the Protector? What the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Parliament? What is a Parliament? VVhich of theſe is Supreme? To whom ſhall any man make his obedience? And to what purpoſe ſhould the reſt of the Members be allowed to ſit, and another Houſe made, when theſe onely who are now admitted, with the Protector, can make Laws without them? VVhether is the Protector obliged to obſerve the Inſtrument, or the Humble Petition and Advice, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſworn to both? Nor would the Protector ſuffer this Parliament to ſit after this expectation, ſo long as to paſs one Act conjunctly with the Other Houſe.</p>
            <p>Since, <hi>Sept.</hi> 3. 1658. Death made another altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by taking away the Protector, <hi>Oliver,</hi> by the Grace of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and they ſay that he deſigned his Son <hi>Richard</hi> his Succeſſor, who did ſwear, they ſay, to protect and govern this free-born people ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Laws; but what the Laws are, no man can tell, where the Legiſlator is not certainly known. It is a queſtion whether this Protector ſhall be <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> the Firſt, or Second; or whether he be by the Grace of God, or not; claiming all his Right from the Petition and Advice, and his Fathers Nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>But all the World runs a madding ſtill, and is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in nothing but Inconſtancie; and this poor Nation in all theſe changes findes nothing tending to her cure. The Protector calls a company of men to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jan.</hi> 27. 1658.</note> (<hi>viz.</hi> this Houſe, and the Other Houſe) and although he claims all his Right from the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45450:4"/>and Advice, as the chief Corner-ſtone; yet was this Houſe that made the Petition and Advice, in election and conſtitution, nothing like this Houſe, who then aſſumed to themſelves the Supreme Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of this Nation: Theſe men in this Houſe, not onely diſallow thoſe men who framed the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Advice, as no Free Parliament; but having themſelves but an entruſted power (againſt all Rules of Law and Reaſon) participate and communicate this their power to Iriſh and Scotiſh Members; whereas <hi>Delegata poteſtas non poteſt participari.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe they will not be leſs kind-hearted to the Tother Houſe, then their Scotiſh and Iriſh Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, they, for convenience, will tranſact with the Members now ſitting in the Other Houſe, as another Houſe of Parliament. But whether the Other Houſe ſhall be Superiour, Equal, or Inferiour to this, may be a great Queſtion: If Superiour to this, then cannot this be the Supreme Authority of this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; nay, then cannot they be made and created by this Houſe; for no created Thing can be ſuperior to its Maker and Creator: If Equal, then cannot it be the Other Houſe, but a part or relative to this; which muſt needs be a breach of the Truſt of this Houſe; nor ſhall ever the free-born people of this Nation need to elect Members to this Houſe, if this Houſe can make Members of their own Scotiſh and Iriſh, and another Houſe of like Authority with themſelves: If the Other Houſe be Inferiour to this, then are the Lords, and alwayes-received Upper-Houſe of Parliament, inferiour, and ſubject to the Lower Houſe, and Houſe of Commons, the cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thing in the reckoning.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:45450:5"/>
            <p>It is a ſtrange thing to conſider, what a frenzie and madneſs this Nation is fallen into, ſince 1641. when under a gratious and known Soveraign, and received and known Laws, the greateſt bleſſings (in the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary nature of things) God can give a Nation; not onely eſteeming Liberty in the multiplicity of Laws, and uncertain Governours,<note n="(g)" place="margin">As if it were intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to obey one known Soveraign, and known Laws, and yet an caſie thing to be inſlaved to the arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wills and luſts of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men, who by no Right tyrannize over us.</note> but by their wilful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting their known Prince and Laws, they labour under all thoſe Miſeries and Calamities which are incident to Confuſion; and yet think there is no way to peace, but the contrary extreme. If any man before theſe times ſhould have named but the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of Exciſe, (the moſt tolerable of Taxes we now groan under) I am confident he would have been pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in pieces by the Multitude. And after all theſe publique Impoſitions, and Taxes, ſince 1641. (which I am confident are twenty times more then all the Taxes in five hundred years under our Kings) and the ſale of the Crown and Church Lands, (the one, the greateſt Ornament of our Nation; the other, of our Church) there is now a greater publick Debt upon this Nation, then all the Texes impoſed by, or given to the Kings of <hi>England</hi> theſe hundred years, will ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie; though not above two years ago, a conſtant Salary was conſtituted, ſufficient to defray the charge of the Army and Navy.</p>
            <p>They were wont to cry out of, and to fear Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry power, whenas they felt it not, or ſuffered under it: what but Arbitrary power, hath deſtroyed all the known Laws and Liberties of this Church and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? What but an Arbitrary power has brought us into ſuch a condition, that we know not what is Juſt and Legal, and what is not? And if it be a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45450:5"/>miſerable ſlavery where the Law is wandring and uncertain; what a miſerable ſlavery are we fallen into? whereas Incertainty is the onely Certainty of our Condition, and Perjury the leaſt of our Crimes. At firſt men proteſted to be true to the King, and the Proteſtant Religion, as it was eſtabliſhed: after, they covenanted to be true and faithful to the King, in order to the Solemn League and Covenant: then engaged to be true to a Government without King or Houſe of Lords: but that not being conſiſtent with the late Protectors greatneſs, was repealed by a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament (ſo called, of his own making:) then the Protector and his creatures ſwear to an Inſtrument of their own making: but this continued no longer then the Parliament (ſo called) which made the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition and Advice, and they made a new oath to be taken by the Protector, his Council, and all who ſhall ſit in Parliament, or bear Office in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth. I do wonder which of the Members in any of theſe laſt Parliaments, after they came into the Houſe, ever regarded what he had ſworn at the Door: as if the being a Member had been ſufficient priviledge againſt perjury: and let any ſober Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian lay his hand upon his heart, and conſider whether here has not been ſwearing and forſwearing ſufficient to ſwear all Religion of an Oath, as well as Truth and Integrity, quite out of doors for ever: and what Converſation, Truth, Integrity or Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity can be expected from thoſe men in ordinary things, who in things of higheſt concernment, have ſo often violated and falſified their Faith, Troth and Oathes.</p>
            <p>But miſerable ſure is it with thoſe men whoſe ills
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45450:6"/>cannot be ſafe without attempting greater. To all our antecedent Diſtractions and Confuſions, is yet added another, of the Officers of the Army; and where it will end, God onely knows. Theſe men, they ſay, pretending great dangers and fears to the Saints, get leave of the Protector to aſſemble and adviſe for ſafety and redreſs; where, after faſting and long Prayer, they promulge a Petition to the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, teſtifying their great care of him, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and conſervation of his glorious Fathers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Memory: but it is a peculiar mark of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, eſpecially after a Faſt, with theſe Saints, that men never underſtand their meaning, by any thing they ſay: (the Protectors Father of renowned Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, next after old Satan, the common Father of them all, was moſt excellent at it) for the word was ſcarce cold in their mouths, whenas they not onely diſſolve the Parliament, but uſe the Protector juſt with that Veneration and Obſervance that his glorious Father of renowned Memory, did the King at <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> and <hi>Carisbrook-Caſtle.</hi> Where are all the Hails now, of your Highneſſes moſt obedient Soldiers and Subjects, to live and die with your Highneſs, in the preſervation of the Rights Civil and Religious of this Nation? Who gave, or by what Birth-right do theſe Officers do theſe things. Why may not the Under-Officers do by them, as they have done by the Parliament and Protector? and ſo the common Souldiers and Agitators, by the Under-Officers; and ſo <hi>ad infinitum:</hi> and in what a condition are we the while?</p>
            <p>But although the Officers and the reſt of the lower ſort of Soldiers do not well agree among themſelves,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45450:6"/>but as it may relate to their intereſt, in continuance of their preſent greatneſs, and enjoying the good and fat of the Land; yet for the preſent they ſo far agree (it being the likelieſt means to continue their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) to revive the Long Parliament, (or, as it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, the <hi>Rump</hi> of it) that all they who have continued ſince 1648. (ſome great good was done then, I war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant you) until the 20th of <hi>April,</hi> 1653. may re-aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume their Truſt; and ſo they declare<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                  <hi>May</hi> 6. 1659.</note>: which Declaration was delivered to the old Speaker, by the Lord <hi>Lambert,</hi> the Lord <hi>Cooper,</hi> the Lord <hi>Berry,</hi> &amp;c. I would fain know whether it were not theſe very Officers that cut off the Rump of this long black Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and in utter renunciation of it, did not take new Commiſſions from the late Protector. It is a very great Queſtion among the Criticks, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Rump be the Armies Parliament, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Army be the Parliaments Army.</p>
            <p>Thus have we taken a ſhort view of the Alterations and Diſtractions which have (by Gods Judgement and Juſtice) happened to us, ſince we would wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caſt off our known Governours and Laws. Now let any man, not madly and fooliſhly blinded with vain Zeal, conſider in all theſe Revolutions and Changes of our uncertain and many Arbitrary Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, (who by no colour of Right tyrannize over us) whether all Faith and Religion hath not utterly fled from us? Whether all Laws, by which any Man ſhould direct his Actions, have not been ſhut up in the Arbitrary Breſts of our Lordly Governours? Nay, whether the obſervance of the known Laws (the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Rule of Juſtice, Vertue, and Honeſty) have not been perſecuted by our lordly Governours, as Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45450:7"/>and notorious Vices? Did all the Fields of this Nation ever run ſuch ſtreams of humane Blood, as under them? Did ever all the Kings of this Nation, in five hundred years, exact the twentieth part of Taxes, which theſe new Maſters have done in five? Were not the Nobility and Gentry of this Nation butcher'd, impriſon'd, ſequeſtred, by no colour of Law; and their onely Crime, the obſervance of the Law? And to all theſe Calamities, are not the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Patrimony both of Church and Crown invaded, and made a prey to Souldiers, Sequeſtrators and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe-men? Are we not onely diſſenting and jarring among our ſelves; but at open Enmity, and in the ſtate of War with all the World, and all Trade and Traffick interrupted? Are not theſe Lord Officers (titles their ſaintſhips can eaſily digeſt in themſelves, and an effect onely of the Protectors Tyranny, which they diſclaimed, &amp; at firſt was abominated by them) two parts of this Rump-Parliament, who muſt be not only our Lords and Taskers; but alſo the Takers and Receivers of all the Taxes they pleaſe to impoſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us?</p>
            <p>Things ſtanding upon ſuch a horrid and rotten Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, it was impoſſible they ſhould long continue: But the Generous <hi>Booth;</hi> diſdaining ſuch a company of Pigwidgeon Uſurpers ſhould arrogate to themſelves the Title of Parliament; in <hi>August</hi> laſt, 1659. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied by a gallant Troop of Gentry, oppoſes them, and declares for a Free Parliament: which ſo ſtartled them at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> that they moſt impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently Arm'd and ſent <hi>Lambert</hi> againſt him; (whoſe Victory all prudent Men foreſaw would be more ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible to his Maſters, then if he were vanquiſhed.) All
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45450:7"/>this while, although the Nation were generally en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged with Sir <hi>George,</hi> they not onely left him to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain the united force of his Enemies, but contribute (though paſſively) to his oppoſition; ſo that left a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone (although he did as much more then could be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped from him, as the reſt of the Nation had been negligent in what he expected) he and his Party ſunk under the preſſure of his Adverſaries; yet with ſo ſtrange a Cataſtrophe, that in a ſhort time, without Blood, the Victor became the Vanquiſhed, and the Conquered in the ſtate of a Conqueror.</p>
            <p>For the Lord <hi>Lambert</hi> (as he is called) returning triumphantly to <hi>London,</hi> after his Victory, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining that theſe men who were reſtored by the meer force of the Army, ſhould make theſe Lordly Officers hold their places and greatneſs at the will of their creatures, reſolves to have them diſtinct and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent from them: in order whereunto, they, on the 9 of <hi>October,</hi> 1659. preſent them a Petition (as they called it) which was ſo far from being granted, that the Rump re-aſſume the Commiſſions formerly granted them, and conſtitute ſeven Commiſſioners to govern the Army, during the Rumps pleaſure: which ſo ſtartled theſe Lord-Officers, that on the 13 they reduced them to the ſame ſtate they were before <hi>May</hi> laſt, and reſolve to ſhare all the greatneſs not onely of this Nation, but alſo of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> among themſelves and creatures.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſtrange and unheard-of tumults and altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, no man knowing whither they would tend, rouze the Northern Lyon, (who for many years had ſecurely governed a Scotiſh Generation in peace, which none of their Kings before him could ever do)
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45450:8"/>and he declares againſt theſe tumults and diſorders of the Engliſh Army. Againſt him the Officers ſend their victorious General Lord <hi>Lambert;</hi> but General <hi>Monk</hi> being a prudent Manager of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, and having no body to depend upon, oppoſes him upon a defenſive poſture, reſolving to put no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing upon Fortune, which he had ſecurely in his own hands; whereas <hi>Lambert</hi> expecting Orders and Directions from a diſtracted company of Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, whoſe Foundation depended onely upon the wretched common Soldiers, is deſerted, firſt at <hi>Portſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> then at <hi>London,</hi> and laſtly by them all.</p>
            <p>The Soldiers having thus deſerted their Officers, the Rump return, <hi>Decem.</hi> 26. to the exerciſe of their Truſt, as they call it; yet ſo, that they reſolve to keep out a much greater number then themſelves, who by equal right might exerciſe with them; and (not conſidering that their Foundation was only the affections of a company of needy and wretched Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, who expected to derive their pay from them, for want of which, they deſerted their Officers) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed as high and arrogantly, as if they had had the greateſt injuſtice done to them, and been placed in as juſt Authority as ever men had. It is a moſt remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able thing, that theſe very Officers, who not content to have been Lords of the Other Houſe, and to have ſhar'd almoſt all the Military and Civil greatneſs of the Nation among themſelves, ſhould turn out the Protector and his Parliament, and place a thing in ſtead thereof, who in leſs then the Revolution of a Year ſhould take ſo great vengeance upon them all.</p>
            <p>In the Interim, victorious General <hi>Monk,</hi> victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45450:8"/>without fighting, and a Conqueror without bloud, courageouſly advances out of <hi>Scotland</hi> toward <hi>London;</hi> all the way meeting from almoſt all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, Remonſtrances full of diſſatisfaction to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Government; and deſirous of a full and free Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, or that the Secluded Members might be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ſit againe. After he arrived at <hi>London,</hi> the firſt ſervice theſe worthy Patriots put him upon, was to make War upon the City Gates and Portcullices; a thing as ill reliſhing the greatneſs of his ſpirit and undertakings, as hateful and ridiculous to men in general: the baſeneſs of which Action, together with the Reaſons alledged by the Secluded Members, it may be was the cauſe of their re-admiſſion and Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>Upon the 16 of this Month of <hi>March,</hi> this many Tailed and many Headed thing (although they by a moſt unparallel'd fact among them had cut off their Head) called Parliament, which had in ſo many ſhapes acted Tragedies the greateſt part of 20 years, was diſſolved: having againſt all Law and Juſtice, not only been the ruine almoſt of infinite Families of all ſorts of men; and not only cauſed the Fields of the three Nations to run with more ſtreams of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane bloud, then ever was before mentioned by any ſtory of the Nations in many years: but alſo ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted new and unheard-of Courts, after the War was done to, enſnare and take away mens lives: having not only taxed the Subject fourty times more then all the Kings of this Nation have done in 500 years before; but alſo embezel'd and ſold all the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Revenues both of Church and Crown; and yet left a greater Debt upon the Nation, then all the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45450:9"/>Parliaments (except the Sacrilegious gift of Church-Lands) have given to the Kings of this Nation theſe 400 years: having made the honour of the Engliſh Nation vile and contemptible to all Nations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad: having not only loſt all faith at home, but kept none abroad; whereby the Publick Trade and Traffick of this Nation is interrupted and loſt; and yet have left above 50000 armed men, beſides the ordinary Militia, to be maintained by the Nations: yet as an <hi>Epicedium,</hi> to manifeſt their Saintſhips to the world, and how ill the Cavaliers have deſerved, becauſe guilty of none of theſe things, they not only exclude them, but their poſterity, from being elegible in what they call this next Parliament.</p>
            <p>Since it is impoſſible that any differences can be compoſed,<note place="margin">What are the moſt proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble means to cure the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions in the State.</note> where men will not ſubmit to ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and known rule, to which the men differing ought indifferently to ſubmit themſelves; and ſince all Factions have plaid reaks at the Helm, and Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, without all Title or Preſident, not only arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly dominered over one another, but alſo the reſt of their fellow-Subjects; and ſince the forſaking our known Governours, (to whom by all Laws of God and man, we did ow our obedience) and thoſe known Laws, which ſhould be the Rule of the Subjects acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and put a period to their differences, hath been the cauſe of all our civil diſtractions; and ſince there is no other probable means under heaven to cure our diſtractions and compoſe our differences, but by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to our known Governours and Laws: then at laſt, let men lay a ſide all further animoſities, &amp; take hold of thoſe means, which may ſave the Ship of this Commonwealth before it utterly ſinks, to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45450:9"/>ruine of the Inhabitants. But how the wounds of this diſtracted Nation may be ſo healed, and the breaches ſo cemented, that though all be ſufferers, yet the Nation redeemed, will doubtleſs require the wiſdom of a Full and Free Parliament, duly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted; by whoſe judgement all the differences and civil diſtractions of the Nation ought to be determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and decided.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Qui molitur inſidias in Patriam, id facit quod infaelix</l>
               <l>Nauta, perforans navem, in qua ipſe vehitur.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Let us ſee whether, as the caſe now ſtands with us, the condition of this Nation be any better in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then Government. <hi>Credere Deum eſſe, non eſt arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus fidei:</hi> To believe there is a God, is an Article of no mans Faith: nor is that act Religion to worſhip &amp; ſerve God with, which every individual man frames and purpoſes to himſelf as uſeful and expedient for him to do, (yet indeed it is very requiſite, that every man ſhould every day, with his private worſhip and ſervice, implore Gods preventing and aſſiſting grace, all the day after: becauſe no man or men can tell another man what he wants, and to what ſin by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he is evilly prone to, ſo well as himſelf) for then all men who worſhip one God, were of one Religion and of one Faith. Let us therefore ſee what is Faith, &amp; what Religion? Who an Atheiſt, and what Atheiſm?</p>
            <p>Faith is an act of Beliefe in God, as he hath revealed himſelf to mankind extraordinarily,<note place="margin">What is Faith.</note> and ſo as by nature no man could poſſibly without Gods grace, attain to the knowledge or belief of it. It was therefore an act of faith in the Children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45450:10"/>to believe in God as he had revealed himſelf to <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iſrael;</hi> to the evidence of which, no man inſpired with all the knowledge and learning of <hi>Pythagoras, Socrates, Plato, Ariſtotle,</hi> and all other Philoſophers could poſſibly by thoſe helps onely attain; and to believe in God as known to them and their Fathers by the name of <hi>Jehovah,</hi> was an Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Jewiſh Faith: and to believe in God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as he hath revealed himſelf to mankind in his Son <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, God and Man,</hi> is the ſum of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an faith; and by doing in this faith, ought every Chriſtian man to ſeek out his Salvation with fear and trembling.</p>
            <p>By Religion,<note place="margin">What Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</note> all men generally, <hi>Chriſtians, Jewes, Mahometans</hi> and <hi>Infidels</hi> (who though miſplacing the Deity in the Creatures, as the Sun or Moon, an Oak, <hi>Apollo, &amp;c.</hi>) underſtand, the reſtraining or binding men to the Publick worſhip and ſervice of God, in ſuch an unity, form, and communion. And ſo zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous were the <hi>Druides,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Nicias O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. Thuc. l. 7.</note> in their Rites and Forms, that none but their Prieſts and Scholars might learn them; nor would they commit them to Letters, both becauſe they would not have them divulged (leſt they ſhould grow contemptible by being expoſed to the view of the rude and ignorant multitude) and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their Scholars might the better retain and keep them in their memory.<note place="margin">Selden an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>globr. l. c. 4 Ceſar li. 6. de bell. Gall. Camb Br. p. 13.14.</note> If then Religion be the binding men to worſhip God in ſuch a form, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> let us ſee what makes and alters forms. <hi>Forma re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſicut numeri</hi> (according to <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>) <hi>conſiſtunt in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviſibili:</hi> Tho forms of things, as numbers, do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt indiviſibly, or integrally; for as in numbers, if you add to, alter or diminiſh ought from any num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45450:10"/>it ceaſes to be the number it was before; ſo in forms, if you add, diminiſh or alter ought, it ceaſes to be the form it was before: therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts, 1 Tim. 2. <hi>That firſt of all</hi> (becauſe there can be no Religion without it) <hi>prayers, and ſupplications, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions and giving of thanks, be made for all men, for Kings,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And let all things be done decently and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.40. Now decency and order muſt pre-ſuppoſe rules, precepts and formes, to which they are referred; and where there are no rules, precepts, and forms obſerved, there neceſſarily things muſt be done indecently and out of order; and the reaſon of all is, <hi>That men may with one mouth and one mind glorifie God,</hi> Rom. 6.15. And therefore in the Church of <hi>England</hi> (and I believe in all Chriſtian Churches,) ſet forms are not only ordered, when Congregations are gathered together, that many may with one mind and one mouth glorifie God, both for all ſorts of men, in their ſeveral vocations and ſtations;<note place="margin">Flaminem aſſiduum Jovi ſacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotalem erea vit. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy. lib. 1.</note> That as amongſt the Jews, the fire upon the Altar might never go out, ſo among Chriſtians no day might the Prieſt omit to offer up the publick ſervice of God, for all ſorts of men. To believe then in God the Father, in God the Son, in God the Holy Ghoſt, the holy Catholick Church, the Communion of Saints, <hi>&amp;'c.</hi> are Articles of Chriſtian faith; and the worſhiping of God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt in the Catholick Church, and communion of Saints, is an act of Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>Now let us ſee who is an Atheiſt, and what is A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm? there is no man in his wits, that is <hi>compos mentis,</hi> who can think there is no God: <hi>David,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45450:11"/>Pſal.</hi> 14.1. ſays, <hi>The fooliſh body hath ſaid his heart, There is no God:</hi> and 'tis not folly meerly, which makes men Atheiſts; Nor is there any man ſo mad, as to believe there is a God, and he not to be ſerved and worſhipped:<note place="margin">Who is an Atheiſt.</note> who then is an Atheiſt? why he who is of no Religion, that believes there is no God to be publickly and formally worſhipped. And if that be Religion that reſtrains and binds men to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſervice of God, in ſuch an unity, form, and communion; then that is Atheiſm that deſtroys this unity,<note place="margin">What is A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm.</note> form, and communion, and gives liberty or licentiouſneſs to all men to run a whoring after their own inventions.</p>
            <p>Now would I fain know what religion or publick form of worſhip and ſervice of God is uſed among us in Churches,<note place="margin">Whether there be any Religion publickly profeſſed in <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> where it is to be found? In what two Churches is God ſerved with one mind and one mouth? what Miniſter uſes the ſame thing twice? Is not every mans ſoul by an implicite faith, haled before the great Tribunal of heaven in whatſoever the Miniſter ſhall ſay, be it ſence or non-ſence? where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is the decency and order which the Apoſtle com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands? what rules or precepts of God or his Church are here obſerved? and yet if this be not the publick worſhip and ſervice of God, then have the poor auditory nothing but preaching the Goſpel for their money, (unleſs the reading of two Chapters and Pſalms, which is given in to the reckoning.) And now good God, that ever ſuch impudence and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy ſhould enter into the hearts of men, as to call the preaching of the <hi>Chymaera</hi>'s &amp; fanſies of the wild-headed and brainſick men, the preaching of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of Jeſus Chriſt! Sure that which converted the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45450:11"/>world to Chriſtianity, was true: but what man can force a belief to all the contradictions and abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties preached by our new lights? yet every one of theſe hath as much to ſay for his Goſpel one as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>viz.</hi> the taking of each of their bare words for it. God commands <hi>Moſes</hi> to put off his ſhoos, (an expreſſion of worſhip with the <hi>Hebrews</hi>) becauſe the ground whereon he ſtood was holy: but here all are with their Hats on their heads; for which no reaſon can be given, but that all of them might be alike prophane. God in the ſecond Commandment for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids the bowing down to, or worſhipping any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture made with hands (and becauſe all negative pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts pre-ſuppoſe affirmative, therefore this bowing down to or worſhipping muſt be done to ſomwhat elſe) for the Lord thy God is a jealous God; and what is God jealous of there? but that this Divine adoration, which is only due to him, ſhould be given to any creature; and this abſtract adoration, and not concrete, or joyned with any Petition: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when the Devil, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.4, 9. had ſhewed our Saviour all the Kingdoms of the world, and the glory of them, he did not ſtipulate with our Saviour, to ask any thing of him, but told him if he would fall down and worſhip him, he would give him them all: and that this worſhip is due to God, our Saviour ſaith, ver. 10. <hi>It is written, Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi> And all men by nature, whereſoever they conceive a Deity, did and do attribute this worſhip to it. <hi>They bowed themſelves and worſhipped,</hi> Exod. 4.31. and Numb. 25.2, 3. <hi>And the people,</hi> (viz. <hi>the Iſraelites</hi>) <hi>did eat, and bowed down to their gods; and Iſrael joyned themſelves to Baal-Peor.</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:45450:12"/>And how did <hi>Iſrael</hi> joyn themſelves to <hi>Baal-Peor,</hi> but in joyning with the <hi>Moabites</hi> in the worſhipping, <hi>viz. the bowing down,</hi> &amp;c. to their miſplaced Deity? therefore the <hi>Moabites</hi> did bow down to them. And <hi>Judg.</hi> 2.12. <hi>The Children of Iſrael followed other Gods, of the Gods of the people that were round about them, and bowed themſelves unto them,</hi> &amp;c. And v. 17. <hi>They would not hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken unto their Judges, but went a whoring after other Gods, and bowed down to them.</hi> Sure no man can imagine that the Children of Iſrael did more by theſe Gods then the people round about them. And <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. <hi>Whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever falleth not down and worſhippeth the golden image which the King hath ſet up.</hi> And no queſtion this bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down is implyed in the worſhipping <hi>Oſiris</hi> and <hi>Iſis</hi> by the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and of <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Saturn, &amp;c.</hi> by the ancient Heathens.</p>
            <p>And I dare challenge any man to ſhew, where any men do, or ever did conceive a Deity, (until our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers of Faith and Chriſtian Religion left it out) and did not <hi>bow down and worſhip it</hi> with this abſtract adoration. And in reaſon ſhall any man give his ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour (although it may be he never had, nor does expect any thing from him) a Civil Worſhip? and ſhall not I, who am infinitely leſs then a Worm, and no Man, compared with God, (for between us there is no proportion) give this <hi>divine adoration</hi> to God, ſo good and gracious to me, that he has not onely made me, and that not a vile and contemptible Creature, but after his own Image, and indued me with a reaſonable ſoul? And yet with what ſpite and ſcorn was and is this adoration decryed by the Zealots of theſe time, as <hi>bowing and cringing to the Altar?</hi> &amp;c. God no doubt permitting their ſpite and malice to take
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45450:12"/>place among their followers, leſt this <hi>divine adoration</hi> ſhould be offered up to the imaginations of ſuch wretched men. Yet ſhall theſe very men quarrel and fight with the <hi>Dutch</hi> and other Nations, if they do not by ſtriking ſail to their <hi>Admiral, &amp;c.</hi> (though they ask nothing of him) acknowledge their power in the narrow Seas; which is more then they will do by <hi>Almighty God,</hi> in bowing down and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping him. But they ſay, <hi>they worſhip God in ſpirit and truth:</hi> ſo may the <hi>Dutch, &amp;c.</hi> acknowledge their power, for ought they know. Theſe men do more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over inveigh againſt the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> becauſe (they ſay) they commit <hi>Idolatry</hi> in worſhipping <hi>Images;</hi> they themſelves not conſidering, that if this adoration be not due to God, (which in their practice they deny) it cannot be Idolatry to give it to any Creature. With what face ſhall theſe men appear before God, who have for ſo many years together taken the ſacred Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony and means of Gods Church, ordained and given for ſuch an end, <hi>viz.</hi> dayly to offer up the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Church for all ſorts of men in their ſeveral vocations, <hi>to viſit the ſick, to baptize infants, to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the Euchariſt, to bury the dead, to inſtruct the ignorant, to reduce ſuch as walk out of the way,</hi> &amp;c. and in ſtead of theſe, become onely Time-ſervers, ſtudying how to pleaſe them who pay them their wages? And if God ſo ſeverely puniſhed <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> Exod. 10. the ſons of <hi>Aaron,</hi> for once offering up ſtrange fire; what ſhall theſe men expect, who for ſo many years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have offered up nothing elſe but ſtrange fire? Which of all theſe men bows his knee at the Name of Jeſus, though expreſly commanded? would any man take any of them for Chriſtians? Compare the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45450:13"/>ſpirit of our Profeſſors, who have reduced all Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick in the publick ſervice to the ſinging of <hi>Tom. Stern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds</hi> and <hi>Hopkins</hi> Pſalm, with the Spirit of God, 150 Pſalm. <hi>De Jove quid ſentis?</hi> I wonder what the men of this age think of God; what is become of that ghoſtly power, which our Saviour inſtituted in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, Prieſts, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> Sure it is not to be found with the late Tryers at <hi>White-hall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, Oh that I could more then pour forth all <hi>Jeremiahs</hi> Lamentations in Commiſeration of thee, O my Mother Church and Native Country! much more deſerving it, then the Jews did in the Babyloniſh Captivity; for there the Prophet fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw their deliverance, and the promiſed Meſſias; whereas we cannot hope but that Chriſtianity it ſelf is in the wain with us, whenas not onely Biſhops and Prieſts are hated, perſecuted and deſpiſed for no cauſe, but becauſe they are Chriſts Miniſters; and Mountebanks, Puppets and Tryers ſet up in ſtead, and in deteſtation of them; whenas not onely days are kept for the effuſion of Chriſtian blood, moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianly ſhed; and all thoſe ſolemn days and times for the celebration of the myſteries of our Saviours Nativity, Death, Paſſion, Aſcention, and the coming of the Holy Ghoſt upon Men, are by publick Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity decryed as ſuperſtitious and idolatrous; when as no man is qualified for Saintſhip, that cannot ſhew ſome badge of Sacriledge, but alſo the defacing of thoſe goodly Monuments built and founded by our pious Anceſtors for the celebration of the publick worſhip and ſervice of God, and the greateſt Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Engliſh Nation, are numbred amongſt their glorious actions. The Prophet <hi>David</hi> complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45450:13"/>bitterly that in his time the carved Work of Gods Houſe was broken down with Axes and Hammers; whereas here not onely the carved Work of Gods Houſe is broken down with Axes and Hammers, but Gods Houſe it ſelf is made a Jakes, and ſtable for Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Our Saviour whipped the Money-Changers and ſellers of Doves out of the Temple, becauſe Gods Houſe was called a Houſe of Prayer: we have not onely perverted the end of Gods Houſe; from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Houſe of Prayer, and made it a Houſe of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the vile paſſions and affections of ſeditious men; but made it a Publick Exchange, not onely for Money-Changers, but alſo for all ſorts of Paltry Ribband, and indeed of all ſorts of Ribauldry; ſince not half of this Profaneſs was ever heard of in the <hi>African</hi> Churches; where (were it not for ſome poor Chriſtian Slaves) there are no footſteps of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity left: and yet after all this abomination of deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and myſtery of Iniquity, are men ſo general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly careleſs of redreſs, that they apprehend that the onely virtue, which is onely incident to fools and madmen, <hi>viz.</hi> to cure ſuppoſed Vices by running in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to contrary Extreams, until in the end they arrive at right-down Infidelity and Atheiſm. Sure if there were no Faith or Religion in us as Chriſtians, nor any ſenſe of the honour of the Engliſh Nation; yet in Reaſon and Prudence, we (in all this confuſion and diſtraction both of Church and State, which muſt neceſſarily bring deſtruction upon us, if not timely prevented) ſhould conſider of our condition before theſe calamities, (not onely enjoying peace, when all the world were at War; and ſuch plenty and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of all Gods temporal bleſſings, that gold and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45450:14"/>ſilver were almoſt as common as ſtones in the ſtreet; but were the moſt envied and renowned Church of all the Reformed) and return thither, and there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, until we be in ſome ſort aſſured, that by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking our ſtation, we ſhall better our condition, and not run into all Irreligion and Profaneſs.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>A Poſt-ſcript to the Reader</head>
            <p>SInce all theſe Nations have ſo long laboured in ſuch frenzies and diſtractions both in Church and State, and ſince ſo much does depend upon the prudence and temper of this next Repreſentative, in order to the cure of them in either, (the Nation, by Gods extraordinary grace and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy being well-diſpoſed thereunto) it is therefore deſired, that all animoſities, affections, and private intereſt be laid aſide in Elections: and becauſe it may be truly feared, that not onely they who have made, themſelves private Fortunes out of the publick ruines, are not proper Inſtruments for the dementing of our diſtractions, being prejudiced by their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular interest; ſo neither are thoſe men (how worthy and well-deſerving ſoever otherwiſe) who have been much Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers, very proper for Repreſentatives this next Seſſion, leſt provoked by paſſion or otherwiſe, they might rather endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to repair their private, then publick ſtate: nor are
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45450:14"/>men of vile fortunes, who may hope by fiſhing in troubled Waters to better their condition, to be conſidered in this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection; yet are not mens fortunes ſo abſolutely to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, as their parts and integrity: nor are the wounds of this Nation in probability to be ſearched into, and proper Medicines to be applyed to them by men of youth and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, whoſe raſhneſs may produce like effects, to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of others.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
